{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The fluid property, due to which, mercury does not wet the glass is", "opta": "surface tension", "optb": "viscosity", "optc": "cohesion", "optd": "adhesion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Laminar flow of a Newtonion fluid ceases to exist, when the Reynolds number exceeds", "opta": "4000", "optb": "2100", "optc": "1500", "optd": "3000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the momentum of one fluid is used for moving another fluid, such a device is called a/an", "opta": "jet pump", "optb": "blower", "optc": "acid egg", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The normal stress is the same in all directions at a point in a fluid, when the fluid is", "opta": "non-viscous.", "optb": "incompressible.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "having no motion of one fluid layer relative to the other.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Head developed by a centrifugal pump depends on its", "opta": "speed", "optb": "impeller diameter", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydraulic mean depth (Dm) for a circular pipe of diameter 'D' flowing full is 0.25 D. For a circular channel, at Dm = 0.3 D, gives the condition for the maximum", "opta": "flow rate", "optb": "mean velocity", "optc": "both 'a' & 'b'", "optd": "neither 'a' nor 'b'", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The head loss in turbulent flow in a pipe varies", "opta": "as velocity", "optb": "as (velocity)2", "optc": "inversely as the square of diameter", "optd": "inversely as the velocity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most commonly used joint in the underground pipe lines is the", "opta": "sleevejoint", "optb": "coupling", "optc": "flange", "optd": "expansion joint", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Schedule number of a pipe, which is a measure of its wall thickness, is given by", "opta": "1000 P'/S", "optb": "100 P'/S", "optc": "1000 S/P'", "optd": "10000 P'/S", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The net positive suction head (NPSH) of a centrifugal pump is defined as the sum of the velocity head and the pressure head at the", "opta": "discharge.", "optb": "suction.", "optc": "suction minus vapor pressure of the liquid at suction temperature.", "optd": "discharge minus vapor pressure of the liquid at the discharge temperature.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increasing flow rate, the hydraulic efficiency of a centrifugal pump", "opta": "monotonically decreases.", "optb": "decreases and then increases.", "optc": "remains constant.", "optd": "increases and then decreases.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The velocity profile for turbulent flow through a closed conduit is", "opta": "logarithmic", "optb": "parabolic", "optc": "hyperbolic", "optd": "linear", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In case of hydraulically smooth pipe, the resistance to flow depends only on the Reynolds number, whereas for a hydraulically rough pipe, the resistance to flow is governed by the relative roughness. Two pipes are said to have the same hydraulic roughness, when they have equal values of", "opta": "relative roughness.", "optb": "absolute roughness.", "optc": "friction co-efficient for flows at equal Reynold number.", "optd": "all (a), (b) & (c).", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water hammer in a pipeline results from the", "opta": "bursting of pipelines due to closure by a valve.", "optb": "rapid pressure change due to a rapid change in the rate of flow.", "optc": "pressure increase due to closure of a valve resulting in decrease in rate of flow.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Molten soap mass is transported by a __________ pump.", "opta": "diaphragm", "optb": "reciprocating", "optc": "gear", "optd": "centrifugal", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following denotes the effect of compressibility in fluid flow ?", "opta": "Weber number", "optb": "Mach number", "optc": "Euler number", "optd": "Reynolds number", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nominal size of the discharge pipe of a pump is usually __________ the nominal size of the inlet pipe.", "opta": "smaller than", "optb": "larger than", "optc": "same as", "optd": "twice", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The terminal velocity of a small sphere settling in a viscous fluid varies as the", "opta": "first power of its dimeter.", "optb": "inverse of the fluid viscosity.", "optc": "inverse square of the diameter.", "optd": "square of the difference in specific weights of solid & fluid.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the discharge of a centrifugal pump is throttled, then its suction lift", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains unchanged", "optd": "data insufficient to predict", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Foot valves provided in pumps are __________ valves.", "opta": "relief", "optb": "three/four way", "optc": "pressure reducing", "optd": "directional control", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At high Reynolds number", "opta": "inertial forces control and viscous forces are unimportant.", "optb": "viscous forces predominate.", "optc": "inertial forces are unimportant and viscous forces control.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power loss in an orificemeter is __________ that in a venturimeter.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "same as", "optc": "more than", "optd": "data insufficient, cannot be predicted", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The terminal velocity of a particle moving through a fluid varies as dpn. What is the value of n' for Newton's law regime ?", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "1.5", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What is the normal range of exit cone angle of a venturimeter ?", "opta": "2 to 5", "optb": "7 to 15", "optc": "15 to 25", "optd": ">25", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dimension of dynamic viscosity is", "opta": "ML-1T-1", "optb": "L2T-1", "optc": "LT-2", "optd": "ML-1T-2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A particle A of diameter 10 microns settles in an oil of specific gravity 0.9 and viscosity 10 poise under Stoke's law. A particle B with diameter 20 microns settling in the same oil will have a settling velocity", "opta": "same as that of A.", "optb": "one fourth as that of A.", "optc": "twice as that of A.", "optd": "four times as that of A.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The pitot static tube does not measure the __________ pressure.", "opta": "static", "optb": "total", "optc": "difference in static & dynamic", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The fluid in which the shearing stress within it is proportional to the velocity gradient across the sheared section, is called a __________ fluid.", "opta": "Bingham", "optb": "Newtonion", "optc": "perfect", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In fluid flow, cavitation is caused, if the", "opta": "fluid velocity decreases to zero.", "optb": "total energy decreases.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "flow pressure approaches its vapor pressure at the prevailing temperature.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of the depth of flow to the hydraulic radius for the most economical trapezoidal section, in open channel flow is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "1.5", "optd": "2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The drag co-efficient for a bacterium moving in water at 1 mm/s, will be of the following order of magnitude (assume size of the bacterium to be 1 micron and kinematic  viscosity  of water  to  be 10-6m2/s).", "opta": "24000", "optb": "24", "optc": "0.24", "optd": "0.44", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For Laminar flow through a packed bed, the pressure drop is proportional to (Vs is the superficial liquid velocity and Dp is the particle diameter)", "opta": "Vs/Dp2", "optb": "Vs2/Dp2", "optc": "Vs2/Dp3", "optd": "Vs/Dp3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum delivery pressure of compressors can be upto __________ atmospheres.", "opta": "10", "optb": "100", "optc": "250", "optd": "1000", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimension of surface tension is(where, F = force, L = length)", "opta": "FL-1", "optb": "F-1 . L", "optc": "F.L-2", "optd": "F-2 . L", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a dimension-less parameter ?", "opta": "Euler number", "optb": "Specific gravity", "optc": "Fanning friction factor", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Co-efficient of velocity is __________ the coefficient of discharge.", "opta": "less than", "optb": "more than", "optc": "equal to", "optd": "not related to", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "All pipes of a particular nominal size have the same", "opta": "inside diameter", "optb": "outside diameter", "optc": "thickness", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the transfer of solution of thick slurry, the pump used is a __________ pump.", "opta": "reciprocating", "optb": "gear", "optc": "diaphragm", "optd": "centrifugal", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not concerned with the fluid-particle interaction ?", "opta": "Drag co-efficient", "optb": "Froude number", "optc": "Galileo number", "optd": "Weber number", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum theoretical suction lift for water at 15\u00b0C by a centrifugal pump is 34 ft. The same for water at 90\u00b0C will be __________ ft.", "opta": "40", "optb": "34", "optc": "8", "optd": "37", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Momentum transfer in laminar flow results from veclocity gradient.", "optb": "A fluid in equilibrium is not free from shear stress.", "optc": "The viscosity of a non-Newtonion fluid is a function of temperature only.", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pressure drag does not depend upon the", "opta": "roughness of surface of the body.", "optb": "pressure of main flow only.", "optc": "length of the body in flow direction.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dimension of absolute viscosity is", "opta": "ML-1T-1", "optb": "MLT-1", "optc": "ML-1T", "optd": "MLT", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ pumps are axial flow pumps.", "opta": "Turbine", "optb": "Propeller", "optc": "Diffuser", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brownian movement is prominent in the particle size range of __________ microns in case of settling of a particle in a fluid.", "opta": "2 to 3", "optb": "0.01 to 0.10", "optc": "200 to 300", "optd": "100 to 1000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For a particle settling in water at its terminal settling velocity, which of the following is true ?", "opta": "Buoyancy = weight + drag", "optb": "Weight = buoyancy + drag", "optc": "Drag = buoyancy + weight", "optd": "Drag = weight", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Bingham fluid of viscosity \u03bc = 10 Pa.s and yield stress, \u03c40 = 10 KPa, is shared between flat parallel plates separated by a distance of 10-3 m. The top plate is moving with a velocity of 1 m/s. The shear stress on the plate is", "opta": "10 KPa", "optb": "20 KPa", "optc": "30 KPa", "optd": "40 KPa", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the correct statement.", "opta": "A forced vortex occurs when fluid rotates as a solid about an axis.", "optb": "In laminar flow, Newton's law of viscosity does not apply.", "optc": "A free vortex occurs, when fluidrotates as a solid.", "optd": "In turbulent flow, there are neither cross-currents nor eddies.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shear stress in a fluid flowing in a round pipe", "opta": "varies parabolically across the cross-section.", "optb": "remains constant over the cross-section.", "optc": "is zero at the centre and varies linearly with the radius.", "optd": "is zero at the wall and increases linearly to the centre.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The resistance wire used in a hot wire anemometer for conducting electrical current is made of", "opta": "copper", "optb": "tungsten", "optc": "chromium", "optd": "aluminium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}